PAUL JAY: Welcome back to Reality Asserts
Itself on The Real News Network. I'm Paul
Jay.
We're continuing our series of interviews
with John Kiriakou.
Thanks very much for joining us.
JOHN C. KIRIAKOU: Thanks for having me.
JAY: And just to remind everybody, John is
a former CIA officer.
Yes?
KIRIAKOU: Mhm.
JAY: And you'll find his whole biography below
here. And I'm hoping you'll watch the earlier
segments, 'cause this is going to make a heck
of a lot more sense if you have, 'cause we're
working our way through John's life.
You left Greece. You came back in the year
2000, and you're in Langley. You're working
on Greek terrorism. And then 9/11. So where
are you, and how does it affect you?
KIRIAKOU: I was at CIA headquarters that day.
I was supposed to go to the White House that
morning with Cofer Black, later Ambassador
Cofer Black. Cofer at the time was the director
of the CIA's Counterterrorism Center. And
we had a meeting scheduled that morning with
Condoleezza Rice, who at the time was the
national security advisor, to discuss a Greek
issue--which seems quaint now, but I had taken
a call from a driver who said that our car
was ready and to come out to the side entrance
to ride to the White House.
JAY: Now, before we do that trip, what's the
mood at CIA? 'Cause we know now, according
to George Tenet, that he had told President
Bush when he--first presidential national
security briefing, that the number-one threat
to the United States was Osama bin Laden and
al-Qaeda.
KIRIAKOU: Yes.
JAY: That summer leading up to 9/11, Richard
Clarke says, our hair is on fire. We know
now that there were at least four or five,
and maybe quite a few more, very specific
pieces of intelligence that suggested there
was going to be an attack. In fact, it was
even known--some of the people that ended
up on the planes that even had been identified
pre-9/11--there's a lot going on. Now, I know
you're working on the Greek file, but how
much are you getting a sense of this?
KIRIAKOU: Well, I mentioned this in my book.
In July--it was July 6, 2001--I was asked
to spend the day with a visiting group of
Arab intelligence officers. They came to have
a day of briefings and meetings and handshakes
and gift exchanges. And we did this kind of
thing all the time with our foreign partners.
So, as part of that day of briefings, I had
asked for briefings from the Osama bin Laden
group in the CIA's Counterterrorism Center.
Much to my surprise, they did not send a mid-level
analyst, which is what I had expected, to
do this briefing; Cofer Black himself came.
And Cofer at the time was the director of
the CIA's Counterterrorism Center, then called
the Counterterrorist Center.
And Cofer started off this briefing by saying--and
these were his exact words--he said, "something
terrible is going to happen. We don't know
when and we don't know where, but we know
that it's something on an unprecedented scale".
He said, the mood in the al-Qaeda training
camps is one of jubilation. We're hearing
trainers speaking to their students and crying
and saying, I'll see you in paradise. We're
hearing codewords used to describe a major
attack--the salesman is coming with vast quantities
of honey; there's going to be a great soccer
match; things like that. And he said, we've
never seen anything like this before. Our
problem is we don't know when and we don't
know exactly what the target is. And he said,
I beg you, if you have any sources inside
al-Qaeda, please help us.
Well, these guys were silent. I think, frankly,
they were stunned into silence, as I was.
And at the end of the day, after they had
left, I went to his office to thank Cofer
for spending the time doing the briefing.
Again, this was very unusual. And I said to
him, Cofer, I have to ask you, was that for
their benefit, or are things really that bad?
And he said, things really are that bad; we're
going to get hit, and it's going to be terrible.
JAY: This is July 2001. Now, we know there
were various sections of the military intelligence
and other areas of various intelligence agencies
that were trying to model what the next attack
might be.
KIRIAKOU: Yes.
JAY: One of those models for military intelligence
was planes hitting the Twin Towers. One of
them might even fall down. We did an earlier
report on this. Some investigative journalists--Jason
Leopold, was one of them--actually talked
to one of the guys who was running that unit.
That information, as far as we know, was suppressed,
in a sense. It may have not made its way up
the food chain, which was rather odd.
Richard Clarke talks about--in fact, did an
interview just a couple of years ago, which
we also have--we ran on The Real News Network--with
some critical information that never made
it to him. He said that information, in the
normal course of things, would have made it
to him. Someone had to intervene not to let
it go up the food chain.
BOB GRAHAM: Fifty--five-oh--CIA personnel
knew about this. You have to intentionally
stop it. You have to intervene and say, no,
I don't want that report to go. And I never
got a report to that effect.
JAY: We asked Senator Bob Graham specifically
about this memo, Osama bin Laden plans to
attack the United States, that no action was
taken after that memo. Now, you get a memo
like that, and you've got the CIA saying something's
coming, how do you not do something?
KIRIAKOU: I remember Dick Clarke and Cofer
Black both saying that they were shouting
this from the rooftops and no one in the Bush
White House would listen to them.
You're right about the modeling. We knew from
the early 1990s that al-Qaeda was interested
in using airliners as a weapon. The CIA analysis
at the time was that the attack would probably
be against American embassies again overseas,
because they had such great success doing
that in the past.
JAY: Except then you get the memo,--
KIRIAKOU: Right.
JAY: --the memorandum that bin Laden plans
to attack the United States
KIRIAKOU: Well, we wrote the memo.
JAY: Right. You wrote the memo.
KIRIAKOU: Yeah, we wrote the memo.
JAY: The CIA writes the memo to, as a presidential
briefing.
KIRIAKOU: Yes.
JAY: Right.
KIRIAKOU: Yeah. So we had the memo.
JAY: So where [crosstalk] information [crosstalk]
KIRIAKOU: Which information's that?
JAY: That Osama bin Laden plans to attack
United States.
KIRIAKOU: All-source intelligence. The analysts
were able to put that together. And based
on these little bits of information that they're
able to pull together, they decided that the
attack was probably going to be in the United
States, or at least that the intention to
attack was in the United States. We didn't
know that they were already here, because
the FBI didn't tell us.
JAY: This is the group in Seattle.
KIRIAKOU: Well, they were all over the place.
They were in Florida. They were in Washington.
They were all over the place.
JAY: But the FBI did have knowledge of certain--.
KIRIAKOU: Or at least some of them.
JAY: Some of them.
KIRIAKOU: Yeah. Sure
JAY: I think one in Seattle in particular
turned out to be an FBI informant that had
two of the people--.
KIRIAKOU: One of the hijackers?
JAY: No.
KIRIAKOU: I'm talking about the 19 hijackers.
JAY: Yeah. Well, two of the hijackers, apparently,
were staying with a guy, a professor, who
actually had some informant kind of connection
with the FBI, and the FBI didn't tell the
CIA.
KIRIAKOU: The FBI's relationship with the
CIA at the time, and really throughout history,
has been absolutely terrible. We don't like
them, they don't like us. And at least until
September 11, and probably for some time afterwards,
there really was very, very little cooperation.
Now, there were FBI agents, certainly, who
were assigned to the CIA's Counterterrorism
Center, and there were CIA officers assigned
to the FBI's Counterterrorism Center, but
that didn't necessarily mean that both sides
were seeing all information.
JAY: You get a memorandum--and you write a
memorandum; when I say you, I mean the president
gets a memorandum from the CIA saying Osama
bin Laden plans to attack United States--you
guys have intelligence at the level that he
tells you and he tells this Arab country's
intelligence officers that something terrible
is coming on a whole new scale. Why do you
think you cannot get Condoleezza Rice to listen
or the president to listen?
KIRIAKOU: So this is one of the enduring mysteries
of the Bush administration. I don't know why
the Bush White House was not focused solely
on trying to stop this attack.
JAY: [crosstalk]
KIRIAKOU: We all knew what was coming.
JAY: --seemed to be making efforts not to
want to know.
KIRIAKOU: It kind of seems that way.
JAY: I mean, how do you get--Coleen Rowley's
group in Minneapolis can't get a warrant to
go into a computer of a guy that wants to
learn how to take off and not [crosstalk]
KIRIAKOU: And not land.
JAY: I mean, this is--how do you demote Richard
Clarke? How do you have a briefing by the
CIA,--
KIRIAKOU: And they did.
JAY: --who tells you the number-one problem's
al-Qaeda, and you demote your antiterrorism
czar?
KIRIAKOU: That's a good question.
JAY: How do you tell--apparently, the FBI
was told, don't focus on terrorism; we want
you to focus on white-collar crime or something
else.
KIRIAKOU: Right. There was an article just
in the paper saying that the FBI is still
unequipped to handle counterterrorism cases.
Nobody there speaks Arabic, for example. They're
still not focused.
JAY: Well, I guess what I'm suggesting is
that--not suggesting--there seems to be actual
real evidence, hard evidence, that it's not
a lack of focus; they were told not to focus.
KIRIAKOU: By whom? Who does the--.
JAY: By the White House. The White House is
telling the FBI to deprioritize terrorism.
They demote Richard Clarke. And then Richard
Clarke's screaming he can't get their attention
when his hair is on fire. I mean, this is--I
asked Senator Graham this. Well, what do you
think? Is this, like, a deliberate culture
created to not know what's coming? And here's
what he said.
GRAHAM: The fact that it was so pervasive
that virtually all of the agencies of the
federal government were moving in the same
direction, from a customs agent at an airport
in Orlando who was chastised when he denied
entry into the United States to a Saudi, to
the president of the United States authorizing
large numbers of Saudis to leave the country,
possibly denying us forever important insights
and information on what happened. You don't
have everybody moving in the same direction
without there being a head coach somewhere
who is giving them instructions as to where
he wants them to move.
JAY: So that includes before and after the
events.
GRAHAM: Primarily before the event. After
the event, it shifts from being an action
that supports the activities of the Saudis
to actions that cover up the results of that
permission given to the Saudis to act.
JAY: There's got to be a coach. The coach
is in the White House. He didn't say Dick
Cheney,--
KIRIAKOU: Right.
JAY: --but one can--he's not leaving, you
know, much difficulty trying to understand
what he's trying to say here.
What do you think? Was there a deliberate
leaving the back door open?
And let me put one more little piece of context.
We know in the Project for a New American
Century this document that a lot of neocons
signed in the 1990s, which called, essentially,
for the assertion of American military power
around the world to reshape the world. And
it even goes--it goes so far as to say international
law was, like, useful when there was another
superpower, but now it's not really so necessary
anymore, international law. We need to do
the regime changes we need. But they say we'll
never get the American people behind us, because
there's still the Vietnam syndrome, and only
another galvanizing event--I may not be quoting
it exactly, but it's pretty close--galvanizing
event like another Pearl Harbor would create
public support for this kind of a foreign
policy.
Then we get what seems like evidence that
they don't want the agencies to know.
KIRIAKOU: I don't know, to be honest with
you. I can speculate.
I can tell you that the war game model showing
an attack with an airplane was one of hundreds,
hundreds of models. To be able to pick out
one model and say this is the one that it's
going to be I think was probably impossible.
I can tell you, in the CIA I never saw people
work so hard in my entire life trying to disrupt
this attack, and having not enough information
and nowhere near the budget necessary to really
do it.
JAY: And doing it in spite of the White House,--
KIRIAKOU: Yeah.
JAY: --in a sense,--
JAY: --because the White House is not listening
to their own CIA director.
KIRIAKOU: They're not listening, they're not
cooperating, and they're offering appropriate
funding.
Now, Dick Clarke, Dick Clarke was a hero of
the Clinton administration, but I think that
when the George W. Bush people came into power,
they saw this guy that's been in the same
position for ten years, he's gay, he's a liberal
Democrat; it's time to give him the heave-ho.
JAY: So why not give him the heave-ho?
KIRIAKOU: And they demoted him.
JAY: No, no, no. Why not give him the heave-ho
and put someone else at the same level, with
cabinet-level access, and put in somebody
you like who--I mean, it doesn't have to be
Richard Clarke.
KIRIAKOU: Well, Condi Rice took it over. It
was supposed to be Condi Rice's responsibility,
counterterrorism.
JAY: Well, she's not even listening to the
people who are doing the work.
KIRIAKOU: Well, that's on Condi Rice, isn't
it?
JAY: Well, partly.
KIRIAKOU: Yeah.
JAY: But as I'm saying, there seems to be
a pattern here. It's not like--it's not just
some series of--.
KIRIAKOU: I wouldn't call it hard evidence,
though, like you do. I would call it some
circumstantial evidence.
JAY: There's certainly enough evidence that
it should be looked into, wouldn't one think?
KIRIAKOU: Yeah, I would think so. Sure. But
who in Congress has the balls to even take
something like this up? It's just not going
to happen.
JAY: No, it's not. But the media doesn't have
the balls either.
KIRIAKOU: Well, the media doesn't have the
balls, no.
JAY: After we interviewed Bob Graham, agree
or disagree, Bob Graham is an insider.
KIRIAKOU: Absolutely.
JAY: Bob Graham is a serious intelligence
guy.
KIRIAKOU: Yes, he is. Highly respected.
JAY: After he leaves the Senate, after he
writes this book saying the number-one reason
to impeach George Bush is 'cause he didn't
stop 9/11 when he could have--that's in Graham's
book--after he says that the Saudis are directly
involved--I mean, he says all these things,
and Leon Panetta appoints him to the external
advisory committee of the CIA.
KIRIAKOU: Right.
JAY: Like, he's not a marginal--.
KIRIAKOU: No, no. He's a serious guy. Right.
JAY: A serious guy. So I do this interview
with Graham, and he says all the football
players running in the same direction, and
we're talking about the American intelligence
agencies not being able to pursue what they
find is evidence of a growing plan to attack
America, he says there is a coach. That's
news, right? We send this out to all the news
organizations up and down the United States.
As a release, we offer them the footage for
free. We give them a transcript of the key
sections. Not a single news agency or a newspaper
even calls us to find out what we have.
KIRIAKOU: That's the story of the mainstream
media in this country. They're just not interested
in deep, investigative, serious reporting.
JAY: I mean, I have to say, I think part of
it is is this stuff about the buildings coming
down and, you know, explosives and various
thermal--.
KIRIAKOU: Yeah, I don't believe any of that.
JAY: I think it's actually--you know, I've
told people that believe this stuff, you know,
if 50 years or 100 years from now you turn
out to be right, I actually still think you
should shut up right now, because there's
a real conspiracy--there's at least some verifiable
evidence that there might have actually been
a deliberate attempt to mess with the intelligence
agencies and leave the back door open. There's
at least enough--what's it called?--prima
facie to look into it. And the stuff about
the building just kind of freaked everyone
out so much that it seems so absurd. And even
if it turns out it's true, it gets in the
way of something that is actually there and
verifiable.
KIRIAKOU: Mhm. Mhm. Something important.
JAY: Well, rather important--it's 9/11. If
the thing is--if there is a certain kind of
collaboration, and if it is with the Saudis,
which is what Bob Graham's committee concludes,
that the Saudi government is directly involved
in, in their words facilitating--or Graham's
words, facilitating and funding, then--.
KIRIAKOU: See, I never saw that. I saw Saudi
individuals who--some of whom had ties to
the Saudi government or the Saudi royal family,
but I never saw this as a Saudi conspiracy.
JAY: He says so. He says the committee reached
that conclusion.
My own take, having interviewed quite a few
people that know the Saudi governmental structure,
they describe it more like a feudal structure,
in a sense, that there's--
KIRIAKOU: It is.
JAY: --many power centers.
KIRIAKOU: Sure--well, no. There aren't many
power centers. There's one made power center,
and that's the king. He's an absolute ruler.
But there are influential people around the
country, and their influence is based on the
amount of money that they have. That's been
going on since oil was discovered in Saudi
Arabia.
JAY: So you can imagine that something like
this can happen without coming directly from
the king.
KIRIAKOU: Absolutely. Absolutely. I mean,
look at the bin Laden family. The bin Laden
family, it's a highly respected, old family
in Saudi Arabia, originally from Yemen. The
old man bin Laden was worth billions of dollars,
and it was because he was the country's greatest
construction magnate, and not just for Saudi
Arabia, but first all over the peninsula,
and then really throughout the Middle East.
If you wanted something built--an airport,
a port, hospitals, hotels--it was bin Laden
that did it. No, the bin Ladens have absolutely
no blood ties to the royal family. They don't
even have any marital ties to the royal family.
But the bin Ladens are a force to be reckoned
with in Saudi Arabia.
I think it was people who had bin Laden kind
of money who were involved in funding and
financing al-Qaeda. It wasn't necessarily
the Saudi government. It wasn't necessarily
even members of the Saudi Royal family, although
there probably were a couple of rogues. I
think it was these wealthy businessmen who
really keep the country humming, at least
keep its non-oil economy humming. They were
the ones we should have been looking at.
JAY: I have no idea who's right in this, but
it is beyond belief, is it not, that there
has never been an investigation into what's
in those 28 pages, the 28 redacted pages of
the joint congressional investigation.
KIRIAKOU: Absolutely.
JAY: Graham, without ambiguity, says the word
government. And in the interview I stress
it by saying government. He says the government.
I said, not some rogue princes or something?
He says, no, government. He says they have
hard intelligence, and that it's in the 28
pages, and he's not allowed to say what's
in the 28 pages.
KIRIAKOU: I never saw any such intelligence.
Never.
JAY: But you weren't in that section.
KIRIAKOU: But I spent most of my career working
on Saudi Arabia in one way or another, and
I just never saw anything like that.
JAY: Okay. Alright. We're going to continue
our discussion with John. We're going to pick
up where he was on 9/11 and the atmosphere
in CIA and his role. And he ends up in Pakistan.
Please join us for the continuation of Reality
Asserts Itself on The Real News Network.